<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://gabcvit.dev/</id>
    <title>Gabriel Vitali</title>
    <updated>2026-02-02T22:35:15.710Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <author>
        <name>Gabriel Vitali</name>
        <email>vitali.gabriel@gmail.com</email>
        <uri>https://gabcvit.dev</uri>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://gabcvit.dev/"/>
    <link rel="self" href="https://gabcvit.dev/feed.atom"/>
    <subtitle>Gabriel Vitali's Blog</subtitle>
    <logo>https://gabcvit.dev/avatar.jpg</logo>
    <icon>https://gabcvit.dev/favicon.svg</icon>
    <rights>CC BY-NC-SA 4.0 2025 © Gabriel Vitali</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[I tried Vibe Coding for 4 hours, this is how it went]]></title>
        <id>https://gabcvit.dev/blog/my-first-vibe-coding-experiment</id>
        <link href="https://gabcvit.dev/blog/my-first-vibe-coding-experiment"/>
        <updated>2025-03-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Vibe Coding, as the name suggests. Takes a more holistic look at software development, where specialists are not required to dig deep into a skill or tech stack in order to perform their work and have a final product]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!-- @layout-animated-content-wrapper -->
<h1>I tried Vibe Coding for 4 hours, this is how it went</h1>
<h2>What is Vibe Coding?</h2>
<p><em>Vibe Coding</em>, as the name suggests. Takes a more holistic look at software development, where specialists are not required to dig deep into a skill or tech stack in order to perform their work and have a final product. As someone who have worked more than half of his career switching between BA, PM, UX and Dev roles, it's for me the sweet spot where design, development, and product thinking merge by using AI to speed up and cover for more fine-grained skills, allowing people to create with flow rather than friction.</p>
<p>Instead of having to endure endless courses online to have deep expert knowledge of every role you're gonna perform during the development of an application, vibe coding brings:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>LLM-powered Rapid brainstorming and app concept idealisation</strong></li>
<li><strong>Automatic UX Designing which enables quicker Prototyping</strong></li>
<li><strong>AI-assisted code generation based on design files</strong></li>
<li><strong>Manual adjustments on the codebase</strong></li>
</ul>
<h2>My case study: Developing an astrogoly app in react-native for 4 hours</h2>
<p><strong>Quick disclaimer:</strong> I have already worked on the creation of multiple apps from discovery until first launch and late support, so for me the steps to create such an app were very clear. The speed can always vary depending on the people trying this out and how much effort you want to put on a particular step.</p>
<p>I wanted to use my prior knowledge on the lifecycle for an app development to be conceived until its' release, leverage it with Vibe Coding, in order to have a better perspective on its' potential. <strong>As I was doing this on my free time on a Sunday, I didn't want to spend more than 4 hours</strong>, so I have limited my time to this slot and to see how far I would've gotten with it. This is how it went:</p>
<h3>Step 1: Brainstorming and concept idealisation (10 minutes)</h3>
<p>I have quickly chatted with (OpenAI's ChatGPT)[<a href="https://chatgpt.com/">https://chatgpt.com/</a>] per voice and explained that I wanted to create an astrology app that was simple and intuitive to look and interact with, where an user could pick their zodiac sign and see quickly what the app had to tell them about it.</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">That sounds like a fun project! For an astrology app that's simple and intuitive, here are a few design tips:
1. Clean Layout: Use a clean, minimalistic design with plenty of white space. This will make the app feel welcoming and easy to navigate.
2. Zodiac Selection: Provide a simple way for users to select their zodiac sign, like a dropdown menu or a set of icons representing each sign.
3. Personalized Content: Once a sign is selected, display the horoscope clearly, with sections for daily, weekly, or monthly predictions.
4. Visual Aesthetics: Choose a color palette that reflects the mystical and celestial nature of astrology. Soft blues, purples, and golds can be great choices.
5. User-Friendly Navigation: Keep navigation simple, with a clear back button and easily accessible settings.
Do you have any specific features or elements in mind that you want to include?
</code></pre>
<p>Great start for a brainstorming, I already have some UX defaults I should strive for, coloring suggestions, layout suggestions and even feature suggestions that might be interesting to the user. For me the idea of having a grid for the zodiac signs sounded pretty good, so I expressed that in my response and asked it to generate a wireframe for the UI for me.</p>
<p>This was the final result of our interaction, not too bad, I would've removed the top dropdown element, but as I wanted to design it myself, I can easily just ignore that it's there. As I also wanted to have the astrological in a separate page, I also would prefer to have the grid as 3x4 instead of 4x3 and the astrological text in a separate page.</p>
<p><a href="image.png"><img src="https://gabcvit.dev/images/2025-03-30-blog-1.png" style="width: 100%; max-width: 400px; display: block; margin: auto;"/></a></p>
<h3>Step 2: Designing in Figma (2 Hours)</h3>
<p>With the wireframe on my hand, I have started designing views on Figma. I took extra time here to make sure that components were being properly prototyped, and that the design actually looked good. I'm sure that this step could've been made quicker with another AI-powered tool or feature, but I wanted to make sure the design had a very good look and feel, as well as proper prototyping. (also it was super fun to reconnect with my designing skills, so I got a bit carried away here).</p>
<p>During this step I have done a few prompts on ChatGPT again to ask for its' opinion on the color pallete and the overall &quot;feel&quot; of the design, it sounded very positive and it suggested me fun changes to achieve a cooler design. It was a bit like having a UX-sparring buddy.</p>
<p>This was the end result:</p>
<p><img src="/images/2025-03-30-blog-2.png" alt="Figma screenshot" title="Figma screenshot"></p>
<h3>Step 3: Generating the Code with Vercel's AI (20 minutes)</h3>
<p>Once I had the Figma file ready I went to (Vercel’s v0)[<a href="https://v0.dev/">https://v0.dev/</a>] to generate a first code structure. I wanted to give it a very simple explanation only to tell it the tech stack, just to test how smart It would actually be. This was the prompt:</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">Please recreate the UI shown in the attached Figma URL as accurately as possible.

To implement it: use react-native, expo and typescript.
</code></pre>
<p>The result was a codebase with 12 files, I wasn't able to deploy it directly to a GitHub repo, so I needed to copy-paste them manually into a new project, that process took me a bit of more time than it would've taken someone with a paid plan. This allowed me also to have a brief look at the files I was copying, and so far the quality was pretty good, the code was readable, the Figma prototypes were correctly identified as reusable components and the actions to navigate to another screen was also implemented.</p>
<p>This was the first version of the app after I installed all dependencies and ran <code>npm run web</code>:</p>
<p><img src="/images/2025-03-30-blog-3.png" alt="First result from v0" title="First result from v0"></p>
<p>The icon design was pretty different from the design, also the bottom navigation bar was not sticking to the bottom of the screen once a different one was opened. Which is ok, I wasn't too aware that on figma it was possible to anchor elements to the bottom, so probably v0 didn't understand that it was a bottom navbar by itself.</p>
<p>The Vibe Coder here could definitely write follow-up queries to the chat and ask it to fix its' mistakes, but I was too eager to dive a bit deeper into the code and see what was happening, I gues old habits die hard.</p>
<p>Which brings us to the last step.</p>
<h3>Step 4: Manual fixes (1 Hour and 20 minutes)</h3>
<p>Now it was time to interact with (GitHub's co-pilot)[<a href="https://github.com/features/copilot">https://github.com/features/copilot</a>] and try to fix and address some of the contrasts that the app had form the design. This process required some manual SVG icon imports and recoloring.</p>
<p>Once my 4-hour timer went off, this was the current state of my astrology app:</p>
<p><img src="/images/2025-03-30-blog-4.png" alt="Final result" title="Final result"></p>
<h2>In summary: A game changer for innovators</h2>
<p>After this quick experiment I realised that Vibe Coding and the usage of AI tools in software development offer us a huge opportunity to become more autonomous in the market and to launch new products with way less effort, knowledge and budget. A process that would normally take me days (if not weeks) and lots of prior knowledge in different areas to finish, was covered in just a few hours.</p>
<p>This encourages me to try this out more often, it makes me also reflect if I need to be really working 5x per week from 9-5 in order to develop a product for others, where I could instead be creating things that I'm more interested in on my own.</p>
<h2>Finishing thoughts: the potential risks ahead</h2>
<p><strong>I wanted to finish this blog post on a positive note, but after seeing what happened to social networks and other content creation and news industries after heavy adoption of AI tools and making content creation more accessible to all, I need to raise this concern here as a final thought for reflection:</strong></p>
<p>Making tools more accessible to people in other to empower them to create and have more self-determination is always the right thing to do, on the other hand reckless and heavy adoption was one of the biggest causes for the devaluation of artists, their career and their art thorugh spam of low quality, uncreative and AI-automated content (which ironically was fed content from the very artists damaged without their consent), other issues such as the heavy campaining of fake news by bots and automatically generated content are also extremely concerning.</p>
<p>It all looks very similar to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dead_Internet_theory">Dead Internet Theory</a> and I hope that this doesn't happen to the creation of apps as well. In the startup environment we used to tell young aspiring developers who wanted to publish their own app the following: &quot;Just because you could publish your own app, doesn't mean you should.&quot;, the intent of this sentence was not to discourage people to publish their own app, but to focus harder on the <em>business acumen</em>, what would make their app stand out and be unique compared to the other apps that are already out there serving the same target audience, also to look for cheaper and simpler alternatives to solve the issues of the target audience they're looking at.</p>
<p>App development is of course a completely different scope compared to content creation and it requires a much different set of commitment from the creator to its' creation, such as compliance with data policies and infoSec, following policies from each store they'll publish the app on, app performance and responding to direct user feedback. If app publishers become reckless on these sensible practices and are not taking full ownership of their product, this could be a huge risk to their users.</p>
<p>Let's see how this will go, maybe I'll reopen this topic on another blog post.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Gabriel Vitali</name>
            <email>vitali.gabriel@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>https://gabcvit.dev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The fallacy of measuring performance, Why tech companies get it wrong]]></title>
        <id>https://gabcvit.dev/blog/the-fallacy-of-measuring-performance-in-IT</id>
        <link href="https://gabcvit.dev/blog/the-fallacy-of-measuring-performance-in-IT"/>
        <updated>2025-02-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the fast-paced world of software development, performance measurement is presented to us as a "necessary solution". Companies and management want to ensure that their teams are productive, efficient, and delivering value. However,]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!-- @layout-animated-content-wrapper -->
<h1>The fallacy of measuring performance: Why tech companies get it wrong</h1>
<p>In the fast-paced world of software development, performance measurement is presented to us as a &quot;necessary solution&quot;. Companies and management want to ensure that their teams are productive, efficient, and delivering value. However, the way tech companies approach performance metrics often does more harm than good, sacrificing software quality on the long run in the exchange for the illusion of efficiency and transparency.</p>
<h2>The misuse of some common KPIs in software development</h2>
<p>Many tech companies fall into the same trap of using simplistic key performance indicators (KPIs) to evaluate developers. These metrics include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Story points completed per sprint:</strong> Something designed only for planning, not for performance evaluation.</li>
<li><strong>Number of commits pushed to main:</strong> Incentivizing frequent, but not necessarily meaningful, contributions to the repository.</li>
<li><strong>Lines of code written:</strong> Rewarding verbosity over readability and maintainability.</li>
<li><strong>Bugs closed:</strong> Ignoring the root cause analysis and instead focuses on &quot;just solving it&quot;.</li>
</ul>
<p>These metrics create perverse incentives. Developers naturally start gaming the system: inflating estimates to look more productive, making unnecessary commits, or prioritizing speed over robustness. Instead of improving efficiency, these metrics degrade the quality of the codebase and demotivate engineers who genuinely care about the quality of their code and its' sustainability.</p>
<h2>The complexity of measuring IT performance</h2>
<p>Software development is not an assembly line. Unlike manufacturing, where output can be quantified in tangible units, software engineering is a creative and problem-solving discipline. Some of the most valuable contributions are not easily measurable:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Refactoring code to improve maintainability on the long run</strong></li>
<li><strong>Pair programming and mentoring junior developers, where both participants learn a lot from</strong></li>
<li><strong>Architectural decisions that prevent future tech debt</strong></li>
<li><strong>Writing clear documentation and tests to enhance knowledge sharing and code reliability</strong></li>
<li><strong>Identifying and mitigating security risks before they become a new incident</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>None of these tasks directly contribute to a quantifiable KPI like “tickets closed,” but they are crucial for building high-quality software and add value to the project you're in. The failure to recognize this results in short-term efficiency at the cost of long-term sustainability.</p>
<p>At the moment of writing this piece, I haven't seen a single quantifiable KPI with &quot;hard numbers&quot; which is able to cover all the mentioned items above to properly reward a software developer.</p>
<h2>But wait, it gets even more complicated for IT consultants</h2>
<p>In consultancy, measuring performance becomes even more complicated. Unlike in-house developers who work on a single product, IT consultants (such as me) navigate multiple clients, industries, and needs. Their work extends beyond code – it includes stakeholder management, business analysis, solution design, knowledge transfer, communication strategies and leadership support.</p>
<p>For a consultant, success isn’t about churning out more features; it’s about:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Understanding the client’s pain points and designing appropriate solutions</strong></li>
<li><strong>Bridging gaps between technical and non-technical teams, becoming an active voice and a trusted team member</strong></li>
<li><strong>Ensuring smooth handovers so clients can maintain the system after the engagement ends</strong></li>
<li><strong>Building trust and long-term relationships with clients, safeguarding the account and business success</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>None of these contributions can be boiled down to numbers. Trying to measure consulting work with standard software KPIs is not only misleading but also alienating. It disregards the nuances of client interactions, adaptability, and strategic thinking that make consultants valuable in the first place.</p>
<p><strong>The so-called &quot;soft skills&quot; are, in my opinion, the most important ones a consultant or leader needs to have.</strong></p>
<h2>A better-but-not-yet-perfect approach to Performance Measurement</h2>
<p>While traditional KPIs fail to capture real performance, other companies use a more holistic approach instead:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Team and manager feedback:</strong> Direct feedback from teammates and stakeholders provides a richer picture of contribution.</li>
<li><strong>Customer satisfaction and business impact:</strong> Measuring the impact of solutions delivered, rather than the raw number of tasks completed.</li>
<li><strong>Career growth and skills development:</strong> Recognizing contributions to team learning, mentoring, and upskilling.</li>
</ul>
<p>The measurements above seem to do better at guiding IT consultants into a more reasonable performance and setting more meaninful goals to themselves, in my opinion they are <strong>still</strong> not perfect and should be used with extreme care and transparency by any company that uses it. Making sure that every participant is on the same page on how to build their own goals, how to strive towards them and offering them valuable mentoring during the entire growth process.</p>
<p>As far as qualitative performance indicators go, there is always room for misuse, misinterpration other issues, but that I can write on a future blog piece...</p>
<p>The goal of performance should not be to track meaningless numbers or indicators that tell the board of directors that the &quot;company is doing ok&quot; but to foster an environment where people are motivated to do their best work without having to &quot;play the game&quot;. People will go great lengths if they see meaning on what they're doing.</p>
<h2>In the end, why are you measuring performance?</h2>
<p>Tech companies' obsession with quantitative KPIs often leads to counterproductive behaviors that erode software quality and damage morale. In consultancy, the problem is even more problematic, as rigid performance metrics fail to capture the multifaceted nature of client work. Instead of fixating on numbers, organizations should focus on qualitative assessments, fostering a culture that values growth in skills, problem-solving, and long-term impact. Only then can we create meaningful and sustainable software development practices.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Gabriel Vitali</name>
            <email>vitali.gabriel@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>https://gabcvit.dev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Importance of Decentralization Technologies, Building a Trustless Society]]></title>
        <id>https://gabcvit.dev/blog/the-importance-of-decentralization-technologies</id>
        <link href="https://gabcvit.dev/blog/the-importance-of-decentralization-technologies"/>
        <updated>2025-02-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In an era where data privacy concerns, corporate monopolization, and centralized control dominate the digital landscape, **decentralization technologies** offer a transformative alternative.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!-- @layout-animated-content-wrapper -->
<h1>The Importance of Decentralization Technologies, Building a Trustless Society</h1>
<p>In an era where data privacy concerns, corporate monopolization, and centralized control dominate the digital landscape, <strong>decentralization technologies</strong> offer a transformative alternative. Blockchain, federated networks (like the Fediverse), and protocols such as <a href="https://atproto.com/">ATProtocol</a> (currently used by <a href="https://bsky.app/">BlueSky</a>) are reshaping the way we interact online, reducing reliance on centralized authorities and fostering a more equitable and trustless society.</p>
<h2>What is Decentralization?</h2>
<p>Decentralization refers to the <strong>distribution of power and control</strong> across a network rather than being concentrated in a single entity. In technology, this means systems where no single organization or individual has neither unilateral authority nor full control over it, leading to greater transparency, security, and resilience.</p>
<p>Decentralization can manifest in many different ways depending on the scope it's built for:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Blockchain</strong>: A distributed ledger system that enables trustless financial transactions, smart contracts, and decentralized applications (dApps) without intermediaries.</li>
<li><strong>Fediverse</strong>: A collection of federated social media networks like <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/">Mastodon</a>, where users control their own data and communication instead of relying on corporations like Facebook or Twitter.</li>
<li><strong>ATProtocol</strong>: A decentralized social networking protocol that gives users control over their identity and content across different platforms.</li>
</ul>
<h2>How does decentralization improve what we have today?</h2>
<h3><strong>1. Eliminating the Need for Trust in Central Authorities</strong></h3>
<p>In traditional systems, users must trust banks, governments, or corporations to act in their best interest. However, history has shown how centralized entities can abuse power, leading to censorship, fraud, data exploitation or prioritise profit over morality.</p>
<p>Decentralized networks use <strong>cryptographic proofs and consensus mechanisms</strong> to remove the need for blind trust, ensuring transparency and fairness in a process that is constantly peer-proofed, authorized, stored in a way that is accessible to all and irreversible.</p>
<h3><strong>2. Enhancing Privacy and Data Ownership</strong></h3>
<p>Big Tech platforms thrive on monetizing user data, often without meaningful consent. Decentralized systems shift control back to users by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Allowing self-sovereign identities, where individuals own their digital presence.</li>
<li>Preventing mass data harvesting by design (e.g., <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-knowledge_proof">zero-knowledge proofs</a> in blockchain).</li>
<li>Enabling encrypted, peer-to-peer communication without surveillance.</li>
</ul>
<p>This way, users can finally use their daily apps without the fear that they're constantly being watched by their phones.</p>
<h3><strong>3. Resisting authoritarian biases and improving user accountability</strong></h3>
<p>Centralized platforms have the power to censor content, deplatform / shadow-ban users and even manipulate narratives that they prefer. Not only that but the algorithm also decides what you will see in your main feed and will prioritise based on a set of rules decided by the same &quot;selected few&quot; on C-level of such Big Techs.<br>
By contrast, decentralized technologies:</p>
<ul>
<li>Prevent single points of ruling that enable mass censorship and content manipulation by intransparent algorithm.</li>
<li>Allow users to choose from diverse communities with different moderation policies (such as Mastodon), or users can build and share their own feed, selecitng exactly the users they want to show on that feed (currently on BlueSky)</li>
<li>Promote open protocols that anyone can build upon, fostering digital sovereignty and app diversity</li>
<li>Allow users to edit fully their &quot;user/domain handle&quot;, or in other words, their ID. Such handle follows the same standards for <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1035">domain names</a> and offers as well verification by DNS, so in case an user would use a famous domain name (let's say... <a href="http://apple.com">apple.com</a>), they would only be able to achieve that, if they are actually the owner of such domain and can insert a verification code inside this domain's DNS configurations. That's it, no more fake verification blue badges for sale.</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>4. Increasing Security and Resilience</strong></h3>
<p>A centralized system is a single target for cyberattacks, making it vulnerable to data breaches and hacking. Decentralized networks improve security by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Distributing data across multiple nodes, reducing attack vectors.</li>
<li>Using consensus algorithms (Proof-of-Work, Proof-of-Stake) to ensure data integrity. If a machine is compromised, the other million machines connected to this network will recognize that the data has lost its' integrity.</li>
<li>Making it economically unfeasible to alter historical records (e.g., Bitcoin’s blockchain immutability).</li>
</ul>
<p>In order to compromise such integrity, for instance, of the Bitcoin blockchain a hacker would need to compromise all nodes across the globe at the same time. Such a thing has not happened yet (and it most probabl won't).</p>
<h2>This technology had a pretty bumpy start</h2>
<p>Even though decentralization solutions offer very interesting benefits, it also comes with some challenges nowadays:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Scalability</strong>: Decentralized networks often struggle with transaction speeds and throughput (e.g., Ethereum’s high gas fees before scaling upgrades like Layer 2 solutions).</li>
<li><strong>User Experience</strong>: Many decentralized apps (dApps) require technical expertise, limiting mainstream adoption. The apps to date are not very inclusive for a non-tech crowd.</li>
<li><strong>Regulation</strong>: Governments are still grappling with how to regulate decentralized systems while preserving innovation. Nowadays it seems that governments are busier going against such technology out of fear, than actually trying to make it work in its' favour.</li>
</ul>
<p>Biggest challenge I see nowadays is to offer a thorough analysis of the potential of such technologies to a crowd of people who are not closely involved with I.T. I have rolled my eyes more times than I could count while watching Bitcoin documentaries or reports failing to explain the most basic concepts of blockchain. Statements as simple as &quot;every transaction is fully transparent&quot; get lost in the scandalous condescending statements like &quot;it's magic money used to buy drugs in the deep web&quot; or &quot;it's solely speculatative without any value behind&quot;.</p>
<p>Also I have perceived online how much X, TikTok and Instagram users have grown accustomed with the algorithm which force-feeds them content. Many new users of more decentralized social networks usually react with &quot;this is boring&quot; or &quot;nothing happening around here&quot; instead of trying to understand that they have full control over the content they want to see, and with that power it comes the responsibility that you also should put in the work to build the feed you want to see. The platforms are working exactly as they're meant, but users are having a hard time understanding this power.</p>
<h2>The Future: A Trustless, User-Controlled Digital World</h2>
<p>Decentralization technologies are still evolving, but their potential to reshape industries and digital interactions is undeniable. By reducing reliance on centralized institutions and <strong>shifting power to individuals</strong>, these technologies lay the foundation for a <strong>more open, secure, and trustless society</strong>, without losing sight of personal accountability.</p>
<p>The next steps involve improving <strong>scalability, inclusivity, usability, and governance mechanisms</strong> to make decentralized technologies accessible to a broader audience. As adoption grows, decentralization may become the standard for finance, communication, and digital identity, fundamentally redefining how we finally interact online.</p>
<p>I'm hopeful for the future.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Gabriel Vitali</name>
            <email>vitali.gabriel@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>https://gabcvit.dev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Generative AI, A Weapon of Math Destruction in the Making?]]></title>
        <id>https://gabcvit.dev/blog/genAI-and-weapons-of-math-destruction</id>
        <link href="https://gabcvit.dev/blog/genAI-and-weapons-of-math-destruction"/>
        <updated>2025-01-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[After reading Cathy O’Neil’s brilliant *Weapons of Math Destruction,* I found myself thinking deeply about how her insights apply to the explosive rise of Generative AI...]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!-- @layout-animated-content-wrapper -->
<h1>Generative AI: A Weapon of Math Destruction in the Making?</h1>
<p>After reading Cathy O’Neil’s brilliant <em>Weapons of Math Destruction,</em> I found myself thinking about how would her insights in algorthm and big data apply to the rise of Generative AI (GenAI). While GenAI holds big promises to revolutionize industries, it also risks replicating many of the same systemic issues highlighted in her analysis.</p>
<p>Cathy warned in her book about the dangers of <strong>opaque, unfair, and unaccountable systems</strong>—algorithms that perpetuate biases and create harmful feedback loops. Today’s GenAI systems, despite their transformative capabilities, could easily fall into these same traps if developers do not have these concerns on their radar.</p>
<h2>Key Risks of GenAI Through Cathy’s Lens</h2>
<h3>1. <strong>Opacity</strong></h3>
<p>GenAI systems, like large language models, are often described as &quot;black boxes.&quot; Their outputs, regardless if text, images, or code, are the result of incredibly complex processes that are extremely difficult, if not impossible, to fully explain or completely understand the chain of thought / criteria used for the conclusion.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Problem</strong>: If even developers cannot explain <em>why</em> a GenAI system produced a specific result, how can users trust its' fairness or reliability?</li>
<li><strong>The Risk</strong>: This lack of transparency can erode public trust, making it impossible to hold systems accountable for harmful or biased outcomes.</li>
</ul>
<p>And this is already happening through the extremely rampant adoption of GenAI models in the market withotu the proper scrutiny, for instance when allowing it to read job applications and share outcomes without in an intransparent manner (similarly to the books' case of Apple's CV-reading algorithm which was identified to enforce sexist biases).</p>
<h3>2. <strong>Amplification of Bias</strong></h3>
<p>GenAI learns from massive datasets scraped from the internet—data that reflects the biases, stereotypes, and inequities of our world.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Problem</strong>: &quot;Biased data in, biased outcomes out.&quot; GenAI doesn’t just reflect societal biases; it can amplify them by presenting them as neutral or factual.</li>
<li><strong>The Risk</strong>: Outputs that reinforce harmful stereotypes or exclude marginalized groups can create real-world harm, especially when used in sensitive applications like hiring, education, or healthcare.</li>
</ul>
<h3>3. <strong>Scale and Power Concentration</strong></h3>
<p>GenAI is being deployed at unprecedented scale across industries, from customer service to content creation to medicine. However, much of this power is concentrated in the hands of a few large tech companies.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Problem</strong>: These companies control not only the development of GenAI but also its deployment, creating significant imbalances in who benefits and who bears the risks.</li>
<li><strong>The Risk</strong>: Without proper oversight, these systems could exacerbate inequality, prioritizing profit over societal good.</li>
</ul>
<h3>4. <strong>Feedback Loops of Harm</strong></h3>
<p>When biased AI systems are used to make decisions, they can create self-reinforcing cycles of harm without proper human intervention.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Example</strong>: Imagine a GenAI-based hiring tool that favors candidates from certain universities. Over time, this could exclude talented individuals from nontraditional backgrounds, entrenching inequality in the workforce.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Building Solutions: How to apply what we have seen in this book</h2>
<p>To avoid turning GenAI into a &quot;Weapon of Math Destruction,&quot; we must take proactive steps to address these risks. Cathy’s solutions for algorithmic systems are just as relevant today:</p>
<h3>1. <strong>Transparency</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>Require AI companies to disclose how models are trained, the data sources used, and the biases identified during development.</li>
<li>Encourage the development of &quot;explainable AI&quot; tools that allow users to understand how GenAI arrives at its conclusions.</li>
</ul>
<h3>2. <strong>Accountability</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>Mandate regulations holding organizations responsible for the outputs of their AI systems. The result of an GenAI model cannot be seen as absolute truth or neutral.</li>
<li>Develop industry standards for ethical AI practices, similar to financial or environmental audits.</li>
</ul>
<h3>3. <strong>Fairness Audits</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>Implement regular audits to evaluate the societal impact of GenAI systems, focusing on how they affect marginalized groups.</li>
<li>Include diverse stakeholders in the auditing process to ensure broad representation and fairness. Making sure that the data we feed our models do not echo our own bubble.</li>
</ul>
<h3>4. <strong>Empowered Oversight</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>Create independent watchdog organizations to monitor the deployment of GenAI systems and investigate potential harms.</li>
<li>Establish ethical review boards within companies to assess AI projects before deployment.</li>
</ul>
<h2>The Road Ahead</h2>
<p>As someone deeply passionate about reducing bias and promoting fairness in technology, I believe these solutions aren’t just idealistic. <strong>They’re necessary.</strong></p>
<p>The stakes are too high to ignore. Generative AI is shaping how we work, communicate, and make decisions. If we don’t address its risks now, we risk entrenching inequality on a massive scale.</p>
<p>Cathy O’Neil’s work reminds us that algorithms are not inherently fair, they reflect the values of those who create them. Let’s ensure that as we build the future of AI, we prioritize transparency, fairness, and accountability.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Gabriel Vitali</name>
            <email>vitali.gabriel@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>https://gabcvit.dev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Importance of Test-Driven Development (TDD)]]></title>
        <id>https://gabcvit.dev/blog/the-importance-of-test-driven-development</id>
        <link href="https://gabcvit.dev/blog/the-importance-of-test-driven-development"/>
        <updated>2024-08-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Test-Driven Development (TDD) is more than just a software development methodology—it’s a philosophy that fundamentally changes how we approach coding. Popularized by Kent Beck and detailed in Martin Fowler’s writings, We're gonna do a deeper dive in this post...]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!-- @layout-animated-content-wrapper -->
<h1>The Importance of Test-Driven Development (TDD)</h1>
<p>Test-Driven Development (TDD) is more than just a software development methodology, it’s a philosophy that fundamentally changes how we approach coding. Popularized by Kent Beck and detailed in Martin Fowler’s book and online posts, TDD emphasizes writing tests <em>before</em> writing production code, fostering a mindset of precision and accountability.</p>
<p>As Martin Fowler describes in <em>Test-Driven Development by Example</em>, TDD provides developers with a robust framework for building reliable, maintainable, and high-quality software. Let’s explore the key reasons why TDD is essential in modern software development.</p>
<p>The culture of TDD is specially strong in the company I work, Thoughtworks, one of the main advocating companies of this strategy to-date. It's one of our core values that generates lots of internal discussions and always expands everyone's horizons.</p>
<h2>1. <strong>Improved Code Quality</strong></h2>
<h3>Writing with Purpose</h3>
<p>TDD ensures that every line of code is written to satisfy a specific test case, eliminating unnecessary complexity.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>To quote a sentece from someone smarter than me:</strong>: &quot;The act of writing a test is more an act of design than verification.&quot;</li>
<li><strong>And the outcome?</strong>: Developers create focused, purposeful code that is easier to read and maintain.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Early Bug Detection</h3>
<p>By writing tests upfront, developers catch issues early in the development process, reducing the cost and effort of fixing bugs later.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Real-World Benefit</strong>: A robust test suite prevents regressions and makes debugging faster and more efficient. You can trust your code better, so &quot;edgy&quot; pushes to main can give you more ease of mind.</li>
</ul>
<h2>2. <strong>Enhanced Confidence in Code Changes and refactorings</strong></h2>
<p>TDD enables developers to refactor code with confidence. When a comprehensive suite of tests exists, making changes to the codebase becomes less risky. If you forgot to cover an use-case when refactoring something, its' test will error out.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Another quote:</strong>: &quot;With TDD, tests are not a safety net—they are a guide.&quot;</li>
<li><strong>And the outcome</strong>: Teams can adapt to new requirements or optimize existing code without fear of breaking functionality.</li>
</ul>
<h2>3. <strong>Fosters Better Design Practices</strong></h2>
<h3>Encourages Modularity</h3>
<p>TDD naturally leads to modular and decoupled code, as writing isolated tests requires clear interfaces and single-responsibility components.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Example</strong>: Developers often end up writing cleaner APIs because testability demands simplicity and clarity. It's just more helpful taking this deep breath to explain in english (or another spoken language) what you expect of this function to work in detail, and while doing that, it's becomes much clearer the separation of concerns between the components you will implement.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Promotes a User-Centric Approach</h3>
<p>This for me is one of the most relevant ones. By focusing on test cases that emulate real-world usage, TDD aligns development with user needs. You essentially need to think of the use case that your test will address, and this forces developers to become user-centric before they start writing their code.</p>
<p>When I used to develop before using TDD, I would easily get lost in the technicalities of my implementation, and lose track of the bigger picture of what I'm trying to accomplish. It happened a few times that by the end of my implementation, it was not was the user needed.</p>
<p>With TDD, it's impossible to lose track of where you're heading to, the test will not pass, and you get direct feedback of what you have to do at all times. Even if you get sidetracked, you never lose sight of the &quot;north star&quot; of the story.</p>
<h2>4. <strong>Facilitates Collaboration and Knowledge Sharing</strong></h2>
<p>A comprehensive test suite serves as living documentation for the codebase, helping new team members understand the system. You will spend way less time having to onboard new developers into your code, as the test file for each component will tell them in plain language, what are the expectations and use cases from each one.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Collaboration Advantage</strong>: Tests provide clarity on expected behavior, making onboarding easier and reducing the learning curve for complex projects. Your test files start to work as indexes to explain the component you're working on. I have found them very useful, as a very forgetful developer, to refresh my memory on components I coded years ago.</li>
</ul>
<h2>5. <strong>Long-Term Efficiency</strong></h2>
<h3>Streamlined Development</h3>
<p>Automated tests act as a safeguard during CI/CD pipelines, ensuring that every change integrates seamlessly into the existing system.</p>
<h2>How TDD Fits into Agile and DevOps</h2>
<p>TDD complements Agile methodologies by promoting iterative development, user-centrism, quick feedback loops, and continuous delivery. It aligns perfectly with DevOps practices, where automated testing is essential for robust CI/CD pipelines.</p>
<h2>Challenges of TDD and Overcoming Them</h2>
<h3>Perception of Overhead</h3>
<p>Some developers resist TDD, citing time constraints or complexity. However, as Martin Fowler points out, &quot;TDD is not about speed; it’s about precision.&quot; While the upfront cost may seem high, the long-term benefits far outweigh initial investments.</p>
<h3>Ensuring Test Quality</h3>
<p>Poorly written tests can undermine TDD. Teams must prioritize:</p>
<ul>
<li>Writing meaningful, edge-case-oriented tests.</li>
<li>Regularly refactoring test code alongside production code.</li>
</ul>
<h2>In the end, is it worth it?</h2>
<p>I do not see Test-Driven Development as a coding practice, it’s for me more of a mindset shift that transforms how I build software and who I'm prioritising. By focusing on tests first, developers write better code, catch issues early, create systems that are resilient to change and maintain their users at the center of the entire development.</p>
<p>Adopting TDD may seem challenging at first, and believe me, sometimes I still struggle to start even though I advocate actively for it, but its long-term advantages make it indispensable for building modern, high-quality software.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Gabriel Vitali</name>
            <email>vitali.gabriel@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>https://gabcvit.dev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Agile Manifesto, A Timeless guide to achieve sustainable Software Development]]></title>
        <id>https://gabcvit.dev/blog/agile-manifesto-a-timeless-guide</id>
        <link href="https://gabcvit.dev/blog/agile-manifesto-a-timeless-guide"/>
        <updated>2024-06-21T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Probably this is not the first time you see a developer writing about the famous buzzword "The Agile Manifesto", it I promise you, it will definitely not be the last.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!-- @layout-animated-content-wrapper -->
<h1>The Agile Manifesto: A Timeless guide to achieve sustainable Software Development</h1>
<p>Probably this is not the first time you see a developer writing about the famous buzzword &quot;The Agile Manifesto&quot;, it I promise you, it will definitely not be the last.</p>
<p>If this is your first time reading about it, let me give you a bit of context:<br>
The <strong>Agile Manifesto</strong>, created in 2001 by a group of very experienced and visionary software practitioners, is a set of ground rules (or rather, priorities) which remains a foundational guide for modern development practices. Its principles continue to influence how we approach software engineering, project management, and team dynamics today. When a team tells you that they are an &quot;Agile team&quot;, it means that they prioritize the Agile manifesto over everything.</p>
<h2>Understanding the Agile Manifesto</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://agilemanifesto.org/">Agile Manifesto</a> consists of <strong>four core values</strong> and <strong>twelve principles</strong>, all designed to prioritize adaptability, collaboration, and customer centrism.</p>
<h3><strong>The Four Core Values</strong></h3>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Individuals and interactions over processes and tools</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Agile prioritizes people and effective communication over rigid frameworks or software.</li>
<li>Tools help, but it’s collaboration that drives innovation.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Working software over comprehensive documentation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>While documentation is important, delivering functional software takes precedence.</li>
<li>Agile teams aim for continuous progress, ensuring the product provides real value.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Customer collaboration over contract negotiation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Agile emphasizes working closely with clients to adapt to their evolving needs.</li>
<li>Success is measured by delivering what users truly need, not just what was originally specified.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Responding to change over following a plan</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Agile embraces flexibility, adjusting to new insights and market changes.</li>
<li>Unlike traditional methodologies, it sees change as an opportunity, not a setback.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>&quot;That is, while there is value in the items on the right, we value the items on the left more.&quot;</p>
<h2>Why the Agile Manifesto still matters</h2>
<h3><strong>1. Faster Time-to-Market</strong></h3>
<p>Agile’s iterative approach enables teams to release features incrementally, allowing companies to get real-world feedback and refine their product quickly.</p>
<h3><strong>2. Enhanced Collaboration &amp; Transparency</strong></h3>
<p>Agile fosters cross-functional teamwork, daily stand-ups, and open communication, ensuring all stakeholders remain aligned.</p>
<h3><strong>3. Continuous Improvement</strong></h3>
<p>Agile encourages reflection and iteration, helping teams refine their workflows and increase efficiency over time.</p>
<h3><strong>4. Better Risk Management</strong></h3>
<p>Frequent releases and customer feedback loops reduce the risk of building the wrong product. Teams can pivot early, avoiding very expensive mistakes.</p>
<h2>Agile in Action: Popular Frameworks</h2>
<p>Agile is not a rigid framework, but the philosophy behind every &quot;Agile framework&quot; created. Several methodologies are very famous nowadays in the market which try to achieve Agile principles:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Scrum</strong>: A structured framework with sprints, stand-ups, and defined roles (Product Owner, Scrum Master, Development Team).</li>
<li><strong>Kanban</strong>: A visual workflow management system that optimizes efficiency by limiting work in progress.</li>
<li><strong>Extreme Programming (XP)</strong>: Focuses on engineering best practices, including Test-Driven Development (TDD) and pair programming.</li>
<li><strong>Lean Development</strong>: Inspired by manufacturing principles, Lean minimizes waste and maximizes value delivery.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Challenges in Agile Adoption</h2>
<p>While Agile offers a fair list of benefits, implementing it successfully comes with many challenges which I was able to while working with many different clients:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cultural Resistance</strong>: Teams accustomed to their traditional project management style and Ways of Working struggle a lot to embrace Agile. I have found it specially difficult to pitch for colleagues who found themselves for many years doing the same process and accumulating valuable company knowledge, that in order to embrace Agile principles, they would actually need to share their knowledge widely with their teammates (sharing the secret knowledge that made them special), and be open to feedback from others while doing retros and code review (what has been perceived by them as a personal attack and micromanaging). Let's just say that in the end we had to agree to disagree on a few points.</li>
<li><strong>Scaling Issues</strong>: Large organizations may find it difficult to scale Agile across multiple teams. Many companies I have seen try to coordinate sprints across multiple teams by having equal start and end dates, while Product Managers from all teams try to coordinate their sprints in a way that avoids blockers and enables a smoother cross-team collaboration. Still, it is a lot of effort and energy from the teams to achieve such a harmonious collaboration.</li>
<li><strong>Misinterpretation</strong>: Some teams claim to be Agile but fail to embrace its core principles, what I love to call an &quot;Agile Frankenstein monster&quot;. Usually such monsters are extremely micromanagy, try to constantly manipulate their developers to compromise on very big tasks while downplaying their complexity. The good news is that such aberrations are very easy to identify and address.</li>
</ul>
<h2>In the end, the Agile Mindset matters More than the Framework/Methodology</h2>
<p>Agile is not about blindly following a methodology, as I have seen once in a while. It’s about fostering a mindset that values adaptability, collaboration, and continuous improvement. As the tech landscape gets more inclusive for non-techies and grows its' relevance constantly, the Agile Manifesto remains as relevant as ever, reminding us that <strong>people, working solutions, and responsiveness to change</strong> are at the heart of successful software development.</p>
]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Gabriel Vitali</name>
            <email>vitali.gabriel@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>https://gabcvit.dev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>